Guide to the William Foote Whyte Collections 1919-2000
Whyte, William Foote, Collections
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
William Foote Whyte Collections, 1919-2000
/4346
Whyte, William Foote; Scheier, Jacqueline; Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives
58.1 linear ft.
Papers (documents), records (documents).
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
William Foote Whyte (June 27, 1914-July 16, 2000) was a sociologist chiefly known for his ethnographic study in urban sociology, Street Corner Society. Whyte, from an upper middle class background, showed an early interest in writing, economics and social reform. After graduating from Swarthmore College, he was selected for the Junior Fellows program, where his landmark research was done. After his research in Boston, he entered the sociology doctoral program at the University of Chicago. Street Corner Society was published by the University of Chicago Press in 1943. He spent a year teaching at the University of Oklahoma, but developed polio in 1943 and spent two years in physical therapy at the Warm Springs Foundation. Rehabilitation was only partially successful; Whyte walked with a cane for the rest of his life, and used two arm crutches in his later years. He briefly returned to the University of Chicago in 1944, then joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1948, remaining at Cornell for the remainder of his career. He worked for social reform and social change, directing his efforts toward "empowering the disenfranchized and narrowing the gap between rich and poor." He studied industrial and agricultural workers and workers' cooperatives in Venezuela, Peru, Guatemala and in the Basque region of Spain, as well as in the United States. He authored hundreds of articles and 20 books including an autobiography. He is considered a pioneer in industrial sociology.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Whyte, William Foote, 1914-2000; Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.
Form and Genre Terms:
Papers (documents); Records (documents)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
RELATED MATERIALS
Related Collections:
/4191 AV: ILR School Audio-Visual Department Video Cassette Collection
/4297: ILR School Biography Files
5582: Archives Foreign File (AFF)
6007: U.S. Department of Labor Office of American Workplace Labor Management Cooperation Collected Publications
CONTAINER LIST
- /4058: William Foote Whyte Office Records, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  4 linear feet
- /4087: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1928-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  8 linear feet
- /4094: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1974-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  3 linear feet
- /4102: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1974-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  7 linear feet
- /4149: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1941-1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  22 linear feet
- /4149 AV: "ASA Award Presentation to William Foote Whyte by Jacqueline Scheier" Audio-Visual Materials, 1988-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  0.1 linear feet
- /4151: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1972-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  5 linear feet
- /4163: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1919-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- /4168: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1923-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  1 linear foot
- /4173: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers, 1931-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)